<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God's revenge against the enemies of the church written by T.W.</title>
            <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40679</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19504630</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19504630</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108907</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67322)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108907)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1679:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God's revenge against the enemies of the church written by T.W.</title>
                  <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, XV, 1-3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108907:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108907:1"/>
            <p>GOD'S REVENGE AGAINST The Enemies OF THE CHURCH.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>T. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:108907:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108907:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Sam. 15. 1, 2, 3.</bibl>
               <q>And Samuel ſaid unto Saul, The Lord ſent me to anoint thee to be King over his people, over Iſrael: Now therefore hearken thou unto the voice of the words of the Lord.</q>
               <q>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what Amaleck did to Iſrael, how he laid wait for him in the way, when he came out of Aegypt.</q>
               <q>Now go and ſmite Amaleck, and utterly deſtroy all that they have, and ſpare them not, but ſlay both man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Infant and ſuckling, Oxen and Sheep, Camels and Aſses.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TIme was when Amaleck would have deſtroyed Iſrael; Time is now in my Text, when Iſrael ſhall deſtroy Amaleck. <hi>Go, and ſmite
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108907:3"/> Amaleck, and all that they have.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God will revenge the injuries that are done unto his Saints; Anger may ſleep, but it cannot die. Though it be four hundred year after, God will call the wicked to account: Their poſterity ſhall be heirs of their curſe, as well as of their lands. Whom God hath deſtined to deſtruction, he will raiſe up Inſtruments to effect his own Decrees: Whom God employs, he will enable them to that piece of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice about which he ſets them. When God does for man, he expects that man ſhould do for God. The power he gives us, he intends we ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy in his ſervice. If God gives <hi>Saul</hi> the dignity of a King, 'tis fit that <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould yeild him the duty of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. <hi>And Samuel ſaid unto Saul, God ſent me to anoint thee, &amp;c. Now therefore hearken thou to the voice &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words may be generally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chotomized into two parts.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:108907:3"/>1. A commemoration of what God hath done for <hi>Saul,</hi> made him King; <hi>And Samuel ſaid unto Saul, God ſent me to anoint thee to be King over his people, over Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Declaration of what God would have <hi>Saul</hi> do for him, in theſe words, <hi>Now therefore hearken thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the voice, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the commemoration we obſerve two things; 1. By whoſe miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Saul</hi> was made King, by <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaith the Text; <hi>And Samuel ſaid unto Saul, God ſent me.</hi> Secondly, After what manner he was enſtated in that office; by being Anointed thereunto: <hi>God ſent me to anoint thee to be King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the Declaration of what God would have <hi>Saul</hi> do for him, we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The form of the Injunction, in theſe words, <hi>Now therefore hearken thou unto the voice of the words of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:108907:4"/>2. The ground of this Injunction, the remembrance of an injury; <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what Amaleck did to Iſrael when he came up from Aegypt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Commiſſion granted in it, <hi>Go and ſmite Amaleck,</hi> &amp;c. The hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Text will diſcover the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral branches of each particular. I begin with the firſt general, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of what God had done for <hi>Saul,</hi> made him King; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by whoſe miniſtration he was ſo made, by <hi>Samuel</hi>'s: <hi>And Samuel ſaid, God ſent me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God ſent me:</hi> It was not ſo, for <hi>Saul</hi> was ſent to <hi>Samuel,</hi> and not <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul,</hi> ſo we find it 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9. 16.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Sending does not always imply a local motion, but ſomtimes a mental direction; God's Prophets are no leſs ſaid to be ſent, when they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected their Propheſies to a place, then when they brought them. It is the delivery of their meſſage, rather then
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108907:4"/> their perſonal moving, that ſpeaks them ſent: <hi>I am ſent to thee with heavie Tydings,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Ahijah</hi> to the wife of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> coming to him; though the good old man moved nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from his houſe nor ſeat, ſo we read 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 14. 6.</p>
            <p>So is <hi>Samuel</hi> here ſaid to be ſent to anoint <hi>Saul,</hi> not ſo much in reference to any external motion, as to that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetique inſtinct, whereby he was commanded to anoint <hi>Saul</hi> when he came unto him. But <hi>Saul</hi> in coming to <hi>Samuel</hi> to receive his Royal Uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Expoſitors upon my Text ſay, was a Type of wicked and ambitious men, ſeeking after the outward ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignity of the world. From whence no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>They that are leaſt worthy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, are commonly moſt deſirous of it, and ſeek after that honour which the more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> deſerving accepts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not of, without being ſought unto.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:108907:5"/>
            <p>Never had pride ſo much worth, as true worth has humility. There is no dignities ſo high, which ambition makes not the mark of its own merit: no advancement ſo mean, which hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility thinks not to over-ballance its deſert. Every one thinks himſelf wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of that honour whereunto he aſpires; yea therefore aſpires to it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thinks himſelf worthy of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucifer</hi> could not be chief among the Angels, but he will alſo be as high as God himſelf: <hi>Ero ut Altiſſimus,</hi> I will be like the moſt High, <hi>Iſa. 14. 13. Behold, O Lucifer, thouſands of Angels miniſter unto him, and ten thouſand ſtand before him:</hi> While all the reſt are ſtanding, <hi>Lucifer</hi> muſt needs be ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; <hi>I will ſit in the Mount of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> Iſa. 14 14. O <hi>Lucifer!</hi> If thou hadſt any priority of order, thou hadſt none of Nature; if thou hadſt higher endowments then thy fellows, yet but the ſame identity of Being: If
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108907:5"/> thou wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chief in the ſervice of God, yet not exempted from it: For, <hi>Are they not all made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inistring Spirits?</hi> ſo ſaith St <hi>Paul,</hi> Heb. 1. 14. O proud and ambitious ſpirit! Hadſt thou ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be without God, then under him? Hadſt thou rather be chief in hell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then not as chief in heaven? Know then, that thou ſhalt be tumbled into hell, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 15. And he that would ſit in a Throne by himſelf, Judge of his own Angels excellency, ſhall ſtand before men to be judged for his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels contumacy: ſo ſaith St <hi>Paul, Know ye not that we ſhall judge the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels?</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 3.</p>
            <p>But let me draw down your thoughts from heaven to earth: None of <hi>Gideons</hi> ſons ſo much affected So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Power over Iſrael as <hi>Abi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,</hi> not younger then his brethren ſo much in years, as in worth: The name of Judge was enough for his valiant father; nothing but the Title
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108907:6"/> of King would ſuit with his ambition, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9. 2. None before him uſurped Soveraign power over Iſrael, none that came after him was leſs worthy of it: He was illegitimate in his birth, but execrable in his actions. The blood of ſeventy of his Brethren muſt ſeal the Crown faſter to his head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſolon</hi> too, thought he had had as much worth as beauty, his Father's crown would better befit his head, which yet had more hair then wit: There is no wit againſt the counſel of God, who had deſign'd Iſraels crown for a wiſer head; ſo we read 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 13. But what ſay we next to the Scribes and Phariſees, of whom our Saviour ſays, <hi>That they love to ſit in the chief places in the Synagogues,</hi> Mat. 23. 6. If their ſitting there did become their gravity, ſure I am, their love to fit there did betray their vanity. Theſe are thoſe ambitious affections which are figured in <hi>Saul,</hi> in coming (though
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108907:6"/> unwillingly) to receive his holy Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; which is the ſecond thing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in this firſt general; the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how he was enſtated into this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne Office, by being anointed thereunto with oyl: <hi>God ſent me to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint thee to be King,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As the Office of a King doth enſtate him with power, for the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Juſtice, ſo his anointing to that Office with Oyl, which is ever held for a Type of mercy, doth admoniſh him to exerciſe that power with lenity and mercy.</p>
            <p>Hence Note, That the very acts of Juſtice, muſt be tempered with Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and the rigour of the one, miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated with the lenity of the other. Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments muſt nor take their meaſure from that guilt which did occaſion them. The Father of mercies may be our ſoul-melting preſident in this particular. The very Divels are not tormented ſo much as they deſerve.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108907:7"/> For why ſhould we limit the power of his wrath? Wo, and wo, would be the damned in hell, if mercy were confin'd to heaven and earth; yea even in hell does his mercy tryumph over his juſtice, and abates of the meaſure of their deſerved pains, though not of the continuance.</p>
            <p>But let us more ſafely adore the temporal acts of his Juſtice: Here mercy I am ſure interpoſes, not more willing to mitigate our deſerved pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, then unwilling to inflict what he does: ſo ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 33. The grief which he takes at the miſery of men, ſhews his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs to proceed againſt them; for, <hi>his ſoul was grieved for the miſery of Iſrael,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>Judg.</hi> 10. 16. as if he that did afflict, were no leſs affected then the people that were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. So violent is the heat of this holy contention between his mercy and his juſtice, that it kindles repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108907:7"/> in him: <hi>My heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together: Hoſ.</hi> 11. 8. As if the Prophet ſhould have ſaid, Juſtice can no ſooner get a reſolution of vengeance, but in comes mercy, and turns performing into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting; and repenting, into forgiving: but lo juſtice provoked by man's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in ſin, returns, and aſſiſted by truth, begets another repenting of that forgiving; and then the ſentence of judgement is given forth; according as it is written, <hi>Within forty days, and Ninive ſhall be deſtroyed;</hi> when lo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can be executed, it is revoked; his heart turns within him, and the turning of his heart, ſtays his hand.</p>
            <p>Nay more, when Juſtice does pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and God does puniſh, mercy tryumphs even in that juſtice: Becauſe Juſtice will not turn it ſelf into mercy, mercy will turn it ſelf into juſtice; and that which was juſtice in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, becomes mercy in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108907:8"/> that is wrought by being puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Even the acts of juſtice ſhall ſerve to ſet forth the power of mercy in their happy effects. How many that had run to the very gates of hell in in their proſperity, have been brought home again by adverſity, and ſet in their right way again to heaven. God exerciſeth his juſtice, that he may make way for his mercy: 'Tis our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit he intends by puniſhing, and not our ruine. This mercy then which God doth exerciſe in and among his works of juſtice, is a divine rule for all earthly Potentates to walk by, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in my Text to <hi>Saul</hi> by the oyl, (an embleme of mercy) wherewith he was anointed to that Kingly Office<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>God ſent me to anoint thee to be King over his people, over Iſrael: Now therefore hearken thou to the voice of the words of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. which is the ſecond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, A Declaration of what God would have <hi>Saul</hi> do for him, wherein
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108907:8"/> we have firſt the form of the Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Now therefore hearken thou,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherein each word hath its weight. <hi>Now, Now therefore: Now therefore hearken thou: Now therefore hearken thou</hi> (not to the words, but) <hi>to the voice of the words of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now.</hi> This particle <hi>Now,</hi> hath a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Emphaſis; as if he ſhould have ſaid, O <hi>Saul!</hi> Thou didſt ſin before in offering up forbidden ſacrifice, <hi>cap.</hi> 13. 9. thy detruſion from the Throne of Iſrael was threatned then, Now therefore take heed, offend no more, but hearken to. Note hence.</p>
            <p>Preſent obedience may revoke that judgement, which reiteration of ſin may make inevitable.</p>
            <p>If God's [<hi>Now</hi>] be not obſerved, man's [<hi>Now</hi>] may either never come, or come too late. <hi>Eſau</hi> may ſhed tears for the loſs of his bleſſing, but toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his bleſſing, he doth but loſe his tears; for, <hi>he found no place for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108907:9"/> repentance, though he ſought it carefully with tears,</hi> ſaith St <hi>Paul,</hi> Heb. 12. 17. There is a promiſe made to unfained penitence, but there is none made for it.</p>
            <p>Some ſay the Divels ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if they would, or could repent; but there can be no ground for that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion: and my reaſon is, for that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance can expiate no ſin, for which God hath not better ſatisfaction in the death of Chriſt, and Chriſt died not for the Divels. That repentance which is built upon faith in a perſonal appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Chriſts merit, is only ſaving, and this repentance is given only unto <hi>Abraham</hi>'s children, whoſe ſeed the Redeemer of the world took. But what difference is there between men and divels, if the divels cannot expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate their ſins by repentance, and man will not? They are leſs abhorred that neither do nor can, then they that can, and do not: If therefore the divels
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108907:9"/> neither can repent, nor if they did, could be ſaved by it, they are then worſe then divels who may repent, and may be ſaved by it, and yet will not but continue in ſin. We may ſin as men, but if we do not deſiſt from it as Chriſtians, we cannot perſevere in it but as divels: Sad is their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and full of horrour, whoſe hearts are not ſmitten with their ſins, as well as their ears, whoſe reſolutions are not convinced, as well as their conſciences. It were better for theſe to have died ſoon in their ſin, then to have lived longer to it, they may be a little long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in hell, but they would be a great deal leſs tormented; for in living to fulfil the meaſure of their iniquity, they do but treaſure up wrath againſt the day of wrath: Who ſees not then the danger (I ſay) not ſo much of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into ſin, as in lying in it. It is juſt with God to deny repenrance to them, when it is begg'd, who wilfully neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108907:10"/> it when it is proffered. It is juſt that they that run on in ſin without care, ſhould die without cure.</p>
            <p>Nor is it leſs difficult for the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard to change his ſpots, then the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiope his skin. I mean by the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard (which is a beaſt ſpeckled with the different ſpots of white and black) that kind of ſinner that is neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in good nor bad, but ſomtimes white, by retracting of his ſins, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times black, by re-acting, and falling back into the ſame. By the Aethiope, who is wholly black, I mean, that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner which goes on and perſeveres in ſin. Though there be the ſame diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty for either to recover out of their ſins, yet there may be difference in the condition of the ſinner; for recidua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into ſin, is worſe then continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; for it is no marvel, if they that never felt the horrour of ſin, can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in it; if they that have, can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto it: If they found no horror
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108907:10"/> in ſin, why did they forſake it? If they did, why do they repeat it? If the firſt acts of ſin ſtruck any terror, what a work will the reiteration make in the conſcience? If one divel at firſt could ſo diſturb the ſoul, that it could never reſt, till he had been caſt out, and its ſelf been ſwept with the beſome of mortification, and garniſhed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtian graces, what confuſion will he, with the addition of ſeven more worſe then himſelf, make in the ſoul if he returns? <hi>It is better never to have known the way of righteouſneſs, then after they have known it, to turn from the holy Commandment. 2. Pet.</hi> 2. 21. If it were not wicked to conſult with Witches, why did <hi>Saul</hi> deſtroy them? If it were, why did he afterward ſeek unto them? Surely his former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying them, is ſet down, to note his greater impiety in his after ſeeking unto them. Knowledge of ſin, height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the guilt of the ſinner; and reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108907:11"/> both the guilt and judgement of known ſins. And <hi>therefore ſin no more</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith our Saviour) <hi>leſt a w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſe thing happen to you.</hi> God eaſily forgets our paſt ſins, if the addition of more makes him not remember and recal them: But if they do, he deals with us, as ſome mothers with their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, call them to a reckoning for all together: Which <hi>Samuel</hi> does here emphatically infinuate in my Text, by this particle <hi>Now. Saul</hi> was before for his diſobedience threatned the rejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from his Kingdom; which ſentence preſent obedience may revoke. <hi>Now therefore hearken.</hi> Which brings me to the next term of weight, the illative particle [<hi>therefore] Now therefore;</hi> as if <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhould have ſaid, O King! God hath done for thee, now therefore thou muſt do for God. The Note that I obſerve from hence is this.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more pleaſing then a pious gratitude.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:108907:11"/>
            <p>Obligations and tranſgreſſions are proportionable. By how much the more we are bound to ſerve God, by ſo much the more vile we are if we do it not. The foreſight of our ſins, and abuſe of them, cannot ſtop the current of God's preſent favours: but thoſe favours which do not prevent ſin, do aggravate it. <hi>Go up</hi> (ſaith God to <hi>Moſes) thou and the people;</hi> the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tranſlation renders it, <hi>Tu, &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus tuus,</hi> Thou, and thy people; and the following words render it the more probable, where God aſcribes their eduction from Aegypt alſo unto <hi>Moſes; whom thou haſt brought up out of Egypt,</hi> Exod. 33. 1. But how comes Iſrael, whom God had in ſo many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative and reſpective terms appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to himſelf, how come they on the ſudden to be <hi>Moſes</hi> his people, and charge? Surely <hi>Moſes</hi> his prayer (who was alſo the Mediator of the Law) which only preſerved them a people,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:108907:12"/> made them his people: Now God will no longer be the God of his people, then they are the people of their God: Nor would he go up with them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but there was a myſterie in the reaſon, <hi>I will not go up, leſt I ſhould deſtroy them,</hi> Exod. 33. 3. But yet he would ſend an Angel with them: but what do I read? Will not God go up leſt he ſhould deſtroy them? And yet will he ſend an Angel? What ſhall we ſay then? Is there more mercy in an Angel, then in God? God forbid, Not more mercy in an Angel, but leſs danger to the people; for that high favour, and holy benefit of his divine preſence, would but heighten their ſin, and at once both haſten and aggravate their judgement: It is mercy to the wicked to withdraw his temporal mercies from them; becauſe thoſe benefits which do not more excite men to ſerve the Lord, doth the more excite God to puniſh the men. He will
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108907:12"/> meaſure out a portion of wrath, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his abuſed favours: And in this reſpect an Angel's conduct was more ſafe for a rebellious people, then God's.</p>
            <p>The puniſhment muſt be proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable to the ſin: To ſpeak morally, there can be no ſin more odious to God then ingratitude, becauſe all his favours are wholly undeſerved. Thoſe favours deſerve moſt of us, of which we are leaſt deſerving. Can we cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge any intereſt in the God of love, when that love of God which hath done ſo much for us, cannot perſwade us to do what we can for God? Are his benefits ſo much above the ability of our deſerving? And ſhall our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert be below the ability of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming? 'Tis true, we are not able to pay ſo much obedience as we owe, yet let us not owe what we are able to pay: But make <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Ergo in my Text, become ours too in reſolution,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:108907:13"/> and reſolve it thus in our ſelves: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the bleſſings which we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from God, and therefore we will hearken to the voice of his words. Which brings me from the illative particle, <hi>Therefore,</hi> to the perſonal, <hi>Thou: Now therefore hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en thou;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thou O King! Thou that art ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with Royal Dignity, though others leſs endeared, leſs indebted, may fail of their duty yet do not thou, <hi>Hearken thou.</hi> The Note is this.</p>
            <p>The higheſt preheminence calls for the exacteſt obedience. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Men are better taught by the eye then the ear, and are brought to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe ſooner by imitation then perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and do rather follow the inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, then his inſtructions. God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Abraham</hi> to offer up <hi>Iſaac<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> not to try his obedience, but to prove it. God did not want experience, but po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity example. <hi>Abraham</hi> had been unworthy to be the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108907:13"/> if he had not left his children an example of his obedience, as well as precept.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Eminency of place calls for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; as firſt, for being example of good to others: ſo ſecondly, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouling evil in others. They only may juſtly reprove a ſin, which may not juſtly be reproved for it. <hi>Otherwiſe wherein thou judgest another, thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnest thy ſelf,</hi> ſaith St <hi>Paul.</hi> They carry (like <hi>Urias</hi>) the letters of his own death, the ſentence of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, that preſcribe that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which they do not practiſe. Nor are they more pernicious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves then others; for in that they pull down by their lives, what they build up by their lines; while men are more ready to follow their example, then inſtruction; they do but make the people alſo more knowing to their greater deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not only, either for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108907:14"/> or for liberty of controuling e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in others, that requires obedience in men of eminency; but alſo out of gratitude to God. He is unworthy to be maſter of a family, who is not the moſt godly in it; nor they either of Civil or Eccleſiaſtical honour, whom ſanctity doth not more adorn then their dignity: The divel would not part with honour to Chriſt, without doing homage for it; and ſhall God to man? Or rather, would the divel have worſhip done to him for his fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed promiſes, and ſhall not God for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al performances. God gave man do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over all his works, and writ his Soveraignty in the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſty of his countenance, but ſealed his donation with a precept of obedience; man broke the Seal, and made the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of no validity. The Government both of heaven and earth was given to Chriſt, but even he too muſt bear it upon his ſhoulders, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 6. that is,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108907:14"/> he muſt ſubmit to the Law, and to the will of God, in dying for the ſins of men; <hi>For ſo it is written, In the volumn of thy book, that I ſhould do thy will, O God: Yea, I am content to do it: and ſo became obedient un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o death, the death of the Croſs: And for this cauſe, God hath exalted him, and given him a name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all names;</hi> Phil. 2. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Exaltation is ever either the reward of obedience, or elſe the condition. <hi>Saul</hi> had done no remarkable ſervice of obedience, why he ſhould be made King, yet he was made King, that he might do it. <hi>God ſent me to anoint thee to be King; Now therefore hearken thou to the voice of the words:</hi> He does not ſay to the Word of the Lord, as if it were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken but now; but <hi>hearken to the voice of the words of the Lord,</hi> becauſe there were formerly ſeveral words, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine oracles, as <hi>Exod. 17. 14. Deut.</hi> 25. 17. which did enjoyn upon Iſrael this piece of ſervice, which was reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:108907:15"/> for a tryal of <hi>Saul</hi>'s obedience. The obſervation hence is this.</p>
            <p>The more often and earneſtly Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are preſſed in holy Writ, the greater care is required in performing them, and the heavier judgement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd in neglecting them.</p>
            <p>The dignity of the perſon that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, makes the breach of the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt precept no ſmall offence; how then will he be obſerved in his more ſevere edicts? Take an inſtance.</p>
            <p>What command is more often, and with greater proteſtation and zeal commended to our practiſe, then an holy obſervation of the Sabbath? What precept violated with greater rigour of puniſhment, <hi>Adam</hi> did not more ſlightly forfeit heaven then his poſterity do eagerly purſue the earth. Heaven being loſt, which only can ſatisfie the deſires of men, the world is only affected, which never can. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven innocent <hi>Adam</hi> muſt till the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:108907:15"/> ground, <hi>Gen,</hi> 2. 15. but <hi>in ſorrow muſt he eat thereof,</hi> as the curſe of his ſin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 17. And yet, the ſinful ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> as if they would recompence the loſs of heaven, with the gain of the world, by a piece of the divel's Chymiſtry, turn their neceſſity into delight, and make their curſe their bleſſing; with ſuch ſweet content pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing themſelves thorow with many ſorrows, while they will be rich, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 10. though they forfeit for it, truth, honeſty, grace, heaven, yea and Jeſus Chriſt. For this cauſe, God foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the propenſion of man's will, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the falſe beauty of temporal felicity, would be wholly addicted to heap up theſe earthly treaſures, and find no leiſure for heavenly employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, bound us to the obedience of this command, with a more frequent preſſing it, and by threatning the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation thereof with unavoidable death.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:108907:16"/>
            <p>Remarkable is the ſtory of the man that gathered ſticks on the Sabbath day; remarkable, not ſo much in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the puniſhment that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, but in regard of them that did inflict that puniſhment: <hi>And let all the people ſtone him with ſtones,</hi> Numb 15. 35. Not ſome, but all the people: Every one muſt have a ſtone to fling at the offender, that ſo every one might learn not to tranſgreſs that Law, the breach whereof themſelves had been the puniſhers. If the terror of the death might affright them, their own hands dipt in the offenders blood might make them no leſs aſhamed, then afraid to commit that ſin which themſelves had ſo ſeverely puniſhed.</p>
            <p>As in this caſe of the Sabbath, ſo in all other crimes may the propoſition hold; that a more ſharp chaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſement is due to them, whom a more often preſſing doth not excite to a more ſtrict obedience: which that <hi>Samuel</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:108907:16"/> might gain from <hi>Saul,</hi> he minds him of former words, wherein this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was commanded, <hi>Hearken</hi> not to the word, but <hi>to the voice of the words of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whom the new Teſtament calls the God of peace, in the Old, was ſtiled the Lord of Hoſts. The whole Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Men, Angels, and the other creatures, are God's armies, ſent forth to ſubdue his enemies: <hi>The very Stars in their courſe fight againſt Siſera,</hi> Judg. 5. God is called thus and thus, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his ſeveral attributes: His Attributes are diſtinguiſhed in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men, by their proper actions; from theſe attributes producing acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons anſwerable each to the ſame, are theſe Titles derived. Thus great and miraculous actions, ſpeaks him a God of power. Acts of puniſhment, a juſt God. Acts of grace, a God of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: and Acts of victory, the Lord of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108907:17"/> Hoſts, from whom <hi>Samuel</hi> here brought a Commiſſion; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And what was that?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I remember what Amaleck did. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</hi> Whence note.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the actions of the wicked are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the book of God's remembrance.</hi> Penitently to remember our own ſins, is the readieſt way to aboliſh them. The fight of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erpent cures the ſting. Becauſe the Saints ſets their ſins before their face, God caſts them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind his back, God will not hereafter afflict them for their ſins, whom their very ſins do here afflict. If hell were appointed for ſinners, yet not for thoſe who make their ſins as an hell to them; as he did who prayed, O bring my ſoul out of hell! that is, from the ſtate of ſin.</p>
            <p>'Tis contrary with the wicked, they forget God, and with him, the ſins they commit againſt him: Some waſh away the remembrance of their ſins in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:108907:17"/> their drunken Bowls, as did <hi>Balſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> Dan. 5. Some feaſt away the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them, in luxurious ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot, ſo did <hi>Dives,</hi> Luke 15. Some fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle away the remembrance of them, ſo did they in <hi>Job, They take the Tabret and the Harp, and delight in the found of the Organ,</hi> Job 21. 12. Some ſport a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all thoughts of ſin, <hi>They ſpend their days in mirth, and in a moment go down to death,</hi> Job 21. 13. Some bury the remembrance of ſin in their worldly cares, ſo do the greedy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the earth. Some choak the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of them with a falſe hope, that God himſelf takes no notice of them, <hi>Tuſh, ſay they, Doth God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it? Is there knowledge in the moſt high?</hi> Yes, deſperate ſinner, God doth ſee them, he records them all, and in his time of vengeance, will remember it too. <hi>I remember what Amaleck did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why did the Angel go about Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem in the appearance of a man, with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:108907:18"/> a Writers Inkhorn by his ſide, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. 11. but to note, that if he did not according to the Letter of the Text; write down all their ſins, yet to ſignifie they were as certainly remembred as if they were.</p>
            <p>All holy and divine Attributes make up but one God. All the operations of thoſe attributes, tend but to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh one infinite Will, and terminates in glorifying him. His glory is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, and ſo are the ways whereby he doth promote it. Thoſe ways which are moſt unlikely in the apprehenſion of man, do moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance that glory. Nothing did more ſtartle the faith of the ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, then the proſperous ſucceſs of the wicked: <hi>Why doth the way of the wicked proſper? Why are they in wealth that rebelliouſly tranſgreſs?</hi> cries <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> cap. 12. 2. <hi>Why doth the wicked oppreſs the man that is more righteous then himſelf?</hi> is the complaint of <hi>Hab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakuk,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:108907:18"/> cap. 1. 13. as if they ſhould ſay, Can God be jealous for his glory, and let them proſper ſo, who thus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute it? Is God righteous that takes vengeance on the wicked? Shall man glory in his wickedneſs, and ſhall God ſit down with the diſhonour they do unto his name thereby? But ceaſe, O man, whoſe breath is in thy noſtrils, is the reward of thy faith ſo far above thine underſtanding, and muſt the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of it be only in things below it? Does the wiſdom of God infinitely ſurmount thine apprehenſion, &amp; muſt the proceedings thereof be only li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to it? If God be God, be thou a man. Canſt thou ſearch into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of his mercy, which with-holds the preſent execution of his juſtice, in expectation of repentance? Think not that mercy too great, which had it been leſs then infinite (and ſo above the apprehenſion of a finite creature) had left thee wholly to juſtice? Canſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:108907:19"/> thou ſearch into the ſecrets of his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which raiſeth glory to it ſelf out of abuſed mercy? Think not his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice too ſlow, which had it been more ſpeedy, had cut thee off (thou beſt of men) from the benefit of mercy. Doſt thou ſee a man ſlight the Ordinances of God, and paſs by his gracious call with neglect and ſcorn, to outbrave his conſcience with a bold admittance of any ſin, to aggravate his ſin with hateful circumſtances, in contempt of goodneſs, to be a graduate in ungraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and to wallow in his unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; as if he were as void of fear, as he is of grace; as if he were as far from judgement, as he is from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe. O the dreadful, and no leſs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret effects of divine juſtice. Preſent impunity makes this man ſecure, ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity more outragious: <hi>Becauſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not ſpeedily executed on the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, therefore are the hearts of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men ſet on miſchief,</hi> ſaith the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:108907:19"/> Scripture. It was <hi>Eves</hi> impunity (if I dare ſuppoſe it) more then her exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that induced <hi>Adam</hi> to eat the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biden fruit, He ſaw her eat that morſel which God had forbidden her, but he did not ſee her die, as God had threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her. Me-thinks I hear <hi>Adam</hi> thus reaſoning within himſelf: If the injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction were laid upon her as well as me, why ſhould the penalty be inflicted on me, and not upon her? I may wel hope I ſhall not die for eating that, which I ſee her eat, and live. If <hi>Abſolon</hi> had died for murthering <hi>Ammon,</hi> he had never roſe out of his grave in rebellion againſt his Father. The wicked fear not that vengeance which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently feel not, till they ſuddenly feel what they feared not. Becauſe God winks at the ſins of the ungodly, they think he is blind, and ſees them not: Becauſe they mind not God's judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they think God minds not their ſins: They remember not God's judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:108907:20"/> becauſe he defers them, and God defers them, becauſe he would more ſeverely remember them. <hi>I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what Amaleck did,</hi> which is the next point; wherein two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What <hi>Amaleck</hi> was?</item>
               <item>2. What he did?</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. What <hi>Amaleck</hi> was? He was the poſterity of <hi>Eſau,</hi> the brother of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who was father to Iſrael, to whom Amaleck did this wroag.</p>
            <p>The firſt oppoſition then which Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael received, was from their conſin Germans. To have been the ringlead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of miſchief, is no ſmall aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the crime: The example is as bad as the crime. Every one may ſerve to ſet forward a miſchief, which hath neither skill nor courage to attempt it. What ſhall Iſrael expect from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morite a ſtranger, that is firſt injured by Amaleck a brother? To receive hurt from them which ought to help, is a double injury. No bonds of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:108907:20"/> can reſtrain the miſchievous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of bloody men. Self-intereſt, and envie, know no difference of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but oftentimes produceth the bittereſt enmity between the neareſt allies, as here between Iſrael and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maleck: But if the Law of Nature had link'd Amaleck to Iſrael, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of grace had appropriated Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael to God. Iſraels natural relation to Amaleck, did aggravate Amalecks injury to Iſrael; Iſraels ſpiritual rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, ſhall heighten God's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge againſt Amaleck, for that inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry done to his Iſrael. <hi>I remember what Amaleck did to Iſrael.</hi> And what was that? <hi>He laid wait for him in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, as he came up out of Aegypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He laid wait for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The wicked want nothing but op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opportunity to do miſchief; What they cannot effect by force, they will endeavour by fraud. Amaleck is a true Metatype of the divel, whoſe ſubtlety
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:108907:21"/> muſt prevail more then his power. The divel may roar like a Lyon, but he cannot hurt; he may ſeek to devour, but cannot aſſure it: Not what he will, but what he is permitted, is done by him: yet his malice ſhall ſtill feed his hope. The divel may as well ceaſe to be, as not do like one. Though it be to his greater confuſion in diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he will yet attempt; and hopes to facilitate that by his trechery, which he cannot by his ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Of him it was Amaleck learn'd to lay wait for Iſrael as he came out of Aegypt: For no ſooner can a ſoul go forth in reſolution and endeavour, from the Egypt of the world, to the Canaan of heaven, but that infernal Amalekite lays ſnares to entrap it.</p>
            <p>He that could not endure that man ſhould continue in the ſtate of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, does with greater deſpite behold his return unto it. It is a greater vexation to be foyl'd by a foe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:108907:21"/> overthrown before, and whets the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to a more hopeful encounter. If one divel be expell'd, he will ſeek to regain his poſſeſſion, with the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſeven more. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> cannot endure that Iſrael ſhould ſerve a greater Lord then himſelf, nor the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel a better. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> thinks them ſtrait idle in his ſervice, if they have any leiſure to think of ſerving another, and will encreaſe their tasks, to divert their thoughts. No ſooner could <hi>Gideon</hi> make peace with <hi>Joſhua,</hi> bnt all his neighbour Kings make war againſt him: No ſooner can a ſoul enter into a peace with God, by holy reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of amendment, but the divel ſtrait attempts to corrupt the affections thereof; love of gain, fear of ſcoffs, deſire of pleaſures, in a joynt conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy work together, to break off thoſe reſolutions. <hi>I am the Lord thy God,</hi> ſo begins the Law; but while this Law was writing, the divel ſtirred up the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:108907:22"/> people to force <hi>Aaron</hi> to make them a golden god: While the true God was writing them a Law, they made a Law to ſet up a falſe God. The divel did hope God would hold them unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his holy Law, that had not the patience to ſtay the writing of it.</p>
            <p>Nor ſeeks he more to deprive us of the helps of piety, then to hinder the encreaſe. It is the ſad complaint of many a poor ſoul, that they never meet with more occaſions to call them aſide, then on thoſe days which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent intentions had devoted more ſolemnly with faſting and prayer to humble their ſouls before their God. Holy purpoſes, if deferred, are likely loſt: But its a falſe neceſſity that croſſes that <hi>unum neceſſarium</hi> of <hi>Mary,</hi> which is the only true one, what ever occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is, or outward neceſſity, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts us from our holy purpoſes, it is but an Amalekite that lies in wait by the way as thou goeſt from Egypt,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:108907:22"/> to thy heavenly Canaan, thou muſt ſubdue it; thou muſt deſtroy it in this ſpiritual warfare, as here <hi>Saul</hi> was in this temporal; <hi>Go and ſmite Amaleck, and all that they have:</hi> which is the laſt thing, The Commiſſion granted from the Lord of Hoſts: Wherein ſee</p>
            <p>Firſt the matter of it, <hi>Deſtroy Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The extent of it. 1. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, <hi>All that they have.</hi> 2. Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, <hi>Man and Woman, i. e.</hi> of all ſtates, degrees, and conditions, Infants and Sucklings, Beaſts and all.</p>
            <p>The Obſervation hence is this.</p>
            <p>Divine vengeance knows no differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of perſons, ſpares neither the high for their ſtate, nor the weaker for their Sex, nor the young for their non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, nor the very beaſts for their want of reaſon, which makes them in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves uncapble of finning.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not the high for their ſtate. No outward dignity can be priviledged
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:108907:23"/> from impunity; nay, the dignity of the perſon, adds to the indignity of the crime, and makes him obnoxious to the greater judgement: The reaſon given, is, Becauſe the ſins of the great are exemplary. Great men, if ſinners, are like to the divel, who with his tail drew down the third part of the ſtars with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 4. Who ever knew an holy Court, and a wicked Prince? Or to ſpeak neerer to our ſelves, who ever knew a vertuous family, and a profane maſter? His plenty corrupts him, and he the reſt. They are afraid to appear good, if he upon whom they depend hates to be ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They think he will hate them too, if they be not like unto him. A bad example is ſooner followed, then a good one: It is this in Governours, whether publique or private, that maintains ſin in the world, which it at once both ſecures, and feeds. Men think they may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do that, which they ſee thoſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:108907:23"/> who ought to puniſh it. It is the juſt retribution of God, that if they who ought, do not puniſh ſin, ſhould be more ſeverely puniſhed for it: they attract the guilt of many, by whom many are made guilty: All ſhall ſuffer for their own ſins, but he ſhall ſuffer as much as many, whoſe example made many ſinners. How juſtly did <hi>Dives</hi> fear the augmentation of his own, by his brothers coming into the ſame torments, whoſe example might bring them to it: With what bitterneſs did he entertain the thoughts of their coming to encreaſe his flames, which he already found ſo intolerable? How much better had it been for him to have begg'd his bread with <hi>Lazarus</hi> on earth, then to beg water of him in hell?</p>
            <p>VVhat a corraſive muſt it needs be to the penitent ſoul of <hi>David,</hi> to hear <hi>Nathan</hi> ſay, <hi>Thou haſt made the enemies of the Lord to blaſpheme?</hi> O holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid!</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:108907:24"/> I have heard thee ſomtimes ſay, Thou wouldſt deſtroy all the wicked of the Land? Shall thoſe wicked now learn by thee to be more vile? That thou which haſt ſo often ſang praiſes to the name of God, ſhouldeſt cauſe others to blaſpheme that name! For what will they ſay? Is this the ſervant of the God of Iſrael? Can that Law of God be an holy Law, whoſe chief Profeſſors commit ſuch unholy acts? Such needs muſt be the Law, as the lives of them that do embrace it do declare, Men ſure are ſuch as they are taught to be: If their God were holy, his people would be holy too; he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be good, that hath ſuch wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſervants. If great men therefore be greater examples of impiety, a greater meaſure of puniſhment muſt be their due, which divine juſtice will ſurely pay.</p>
            <p>Indeed it is no leſs requiſite that the Divine nature ſhould be uucapable of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:108907:24"/> ſinning, then impoſſible for it to be ſubject to it: for if it be neceſſary that ſin ſhould be puniſhed, it is as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that it ſhould be puniſhed by him who cannot ſin. VVhere there is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to a capacity of ſinning, there can be no certainty of immunity from falling into it: where there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of immunity from it, there can be no neceſſity of puniſhing it; for how ſhall any (eſpecially eternally) puniſh that, whereof himſelf may poſſibly be guilty, if he ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to it?</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that neither men nor Angels can puniſh ſin; a derivative power they have, but not a primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, they may have it from God, but not from themſelves; they may be executioners of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but not impoſers. The Elect Angels indeed, and beatified Saints cannot ſin; but they have this happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by their confirmation in Chriſt,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:108907:25"/> and not by the ſoundneſs of their own nature: The one have ſinned while they were here, the other might have done even there.</p>
            <p>To God then only it belongs to puniſh ſin, not only as it is committed againſt him, but as it is he that could not poſſibly have ſinned. And now to bring it home, as he is God, and cannot ſin, and therefore only may, ſo as he is God, he cannot but puniſh ſin, and therefore will, in whomſoever he finds it. <hi>He ſpared not the Angels,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Jude:</hi> If ſin ſeizeth upon the nature of Angels, the nature of Angels ſhall be ſubjected even to actual torments for that ſin: As it is written, <hi>Go ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Divel and his Angels.</hi> And as a worthy light of our Church ſaith, <hi>In vain were that light prepared for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, if the Divel's nature could not be tormented in it.</hi> But as for us men, God did more to redeem us, then he did to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108907:25"/> make us. If then God ſpared not the Angels, which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſinned only againſt their creation, how much leſs will he not ſpare man that ſinneth againſt ſo great redemption, <hi>treading under foot the Son of God; as if the blood of the Covenant, wherewith we were ſanctified, were an unholy thing.</hi> Heb. 10. 29. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, If he ſpared not the Angels for their heavenly excellency, much leſs will he ſpare man for his earthly dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; whom their impiety of life doth condemn, their eminency of place ſhall not abſolve. 'Tis the works of men that God accepts, and not their perſons. He that would not accept of a crown for himſelf, will never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of another for it. For, <hi>Tophet is prepared of old, even for the King is it prepared,</hi> Iſa. 30. ult And ſo hateful was <hi>Saul</hi>'s partiality in this reſpect, that for ſparing the King of Amaleck, he loſt the Kingdom of Iſrael, if not of heaven to himſelf. Thus you ſee, firſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:108907:26"/> he ſpares not the high for their ſtate.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Not the weaker for their Sex: Slay man and woman too.</p>
            <p>Women. The original matter of woman, whereof ſhe was compoſed, was more pure then that of man, yet was the woman firſt in the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not the man. Before their fall, ſhe was an help meet for him, not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him; but after her fall, leſt ſhe ſhould abuſe that equality which ſhe had before, to the like ſeducement, ſhe muſt ſubmit to the dominion of her husband, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 16. That as in her equality ſhe firſt induced him to ſin, whereby he merited eternal death, ſo in her ſubjection, ſhe ſhould be obno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious to the penalty of his ſin, even to a temporal death; and therefore ſlay man, yea and woman too.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He ſpares not the young for their nonage. Such as are the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, ſuch uſually are the children; not that the very ſins of the Parents
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:108907:26"/> are by nature transfuſed into the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but do inſenſibly ſteal upon them, by being daylie inured to them, which at length by cuſtome turns to another nature. It is therefore juſt with God, to root the whole race of them, whom he foreſees will be inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritors of their fathers enmity againſt his Church. So <hi>Noah</hi> about to curſe his Son <hi>Cham,</hi> pronounced not the curſe in the name of <hi>Cham,</hi> but <hi>Canaan</hi> his ſons ſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noah</hi> by a prophetique ſpirit fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw <hi>Canaan</hi> would be heir of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſin, and therefore ſubjected him to his fathers curſe. Nay, righteous <hi>Jonathan</hi> muſt be diſpoſſeſſed for his fathers diſobedience. God's judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are always deep and ſecret, but ever juſt: He takes away the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous young for their greater good, he takes away the wicked young for their leſſer torment; and therefore ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay man, woman, yea infant and ſuckling too.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:108907:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Oxen and Sheep, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the endowment of reaſon that gives a capacity of ſinning: The crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is void of reaſon, and therefore free from ſin, yet muſt be ſlain. The unreaſonable creature, though in it ſelf void of ſin, yet in deteſtation of the ſinner whom it ſerves, is made obno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious to temporal puniſhment. If the divel in the ſerpent induce <hi>Eve</hi> to ſin, the inſtrument is curſed, in hatred of the ſin occaſioned by it. In the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the old world by the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal deluge, why ſhould the beaſts, creeping things, and fowls of the Ayr, periſh by the waters, but becauſe they received their food from that earth wherein man had corrupted their ways <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 7. As therefore Beaſts in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral cannot ſin, yet ſubjected to the curſe of man's ſin; ſo neither in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular had theſe Amalekitiſh cattel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hand in the offence done to the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, yet muſt be deſtroyed for their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:108907:27"/> owners ſakes, who had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So ſevere is God's vengeance againſt the enemies of his Church, even total deſtruction, both of them and theirs. In God's due time Amalecks portion ſhall be theirs. Even ſo, O Lord, let all thy enemies periſh, that thy Church may have reſt,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS,</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
